Guide to the New-York Historical Society Museum Store Records 1940s-2001 (bulk, 1980s-1992) NYHS-RG 26
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society museum store records
1940s-2001 (bulk, 1980s-1992)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 26
3.75 Linear feet in 10 document boxes and two oversize folders.
The New-York Historical Society museum store records include documents related to the management of the store, development of its product lines, and marketing. The files include correspondence, sales catalogs, inventories, sales results, reproduction licensing, orders, and photographs of catalog items. There are also examples of some of the products sold at the store, especially small format items like postcards and greeting cards. The bulk of the material relates to the period 1985 to 1991.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society museum store records (NYHS-RG 26) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society building renovations and maintenance records (NYHS-RG 4) include plans from the 1980s to 1990-1991 related to store designs and renovations. Search on keyword "store" in that finding aid.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society museum store records include documents related to the management of the store, development of its product lines, and marketing. There are also examples of some of the products sold at the store, especially small format items like postcards and greeting cards. Correspondence files, primarily involving Director of Store Management Lorelei Rowars, concern proposals from vendors for products and services, arrangements for the creation and stocking of items in the store (including in connection with exhibitions), agreements to conduct sales in locations outside of N-YHS, and customer orders (including expressions of interest from Japan). Financial and royalty arrangements and results are documented in the series, with vendors such as Princeton Audubon Ltd. (Audubon prints) and the Adirondack Store (temporary shop at N-YHS during the Forever Wild exhibition.
The record group also includes detailed documentation of the store's inventory from 1985-1991, which is the principal period documented in these records. The store's first catalogs, from the mid to late 1980s, are in the records, as are some earlier order forms, book lists, and other marketing material. The records include sales results, again especially for the period around 1990. Products included postcards, books, and posters that tied in to the installed exhibitions.
The bulk of the products are cards from the 1970s and later. Yet there are also a small number of items that were sold in the 1930s-1940s, including packets of images and a souvenir booklet (1949).
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society museum store records (NYHS-RG 26) are organized in three series:
Series I. Correspondence Files
Series II. Catalogs and Inventories
Series III. Products
Museum stores -- New York (State) -- New York.; Inventories; Sales catalogs; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; Financial records.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Historical societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; Postcards.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; New-York Historical Society. Museum Store; New-York Historical Society -- Archives
- Series I. Correspondence Files, 1977-1994; 2.17 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This series includes two sets of correspondence files. The first includes correspondence related to the management of the store's product line, with most of the letters directed to Lorelei Rowars, the Museum Store Director from the mid-1980s to mid-1991, when the store temporarily closed for almost five months. Subject matter includes arrangements for products to be developed and sold in the store, such as posters, catalogues, postcards, holiday cards, and other items; product proposals from vendors; arrangements for sales of museum store products through outlets other than N-YHS itself (e.g., holiday gift sales for local company employees), and related matters. These files were found during processing in 2016 as a complete set.
  The second set of correspondence also relates to store management, but was compiled from various store files by the processing archivist. Principal subjects in this set include arrangements for the Adirondack Store to have a space at N-YHS during the exhibition Forever Wild, arrangements with Princeton Audubon Ltd for printing Audubon reproductions, store catalog production files, sales of the Phelps-Dodge Family book, and a sampling of mail orders received for store items.
  Arrangement Note
  The series opens with a set of files in their original alphabetical order by correspondent or topic. These are followed by a second set of correspondence compiled by the processing archivist and arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Set 1. A - Ca, 1977-1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-44)
    Includes exchanges with advertising agencies and outlets (e.g., Forbes Magazines, New Yorker); product development proposals from vendors (e.g., postcards, tee-shirts, bookmarks, calendars); Audubon-related products; book print promotions for the Audubon series, "The Birds of America" and "Immigration to New York"; permissions for American Heritage; Birchrun Mint license regarding John Rogers sculptures; documents from architects Charles E. Broudy & Associates concerning redesign of the store; and poster distribution rights with Bruce Teleky.
  - Set 1. Cl - Lu, 1984-1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-59)
    Includes requests for museum store catalogs; exchanges in regard to N-YHS items to be included in the Museum Shops of the World Catalog; production of circus, theatrical, and Tiffany postcard books (Dover Publications); store consultant Tom Aageson invoices; vendor proposals for various product possibilities (e.g., textiles, notecards, puzzles by Galison Books, address book); arrangements for sale of products, such as posters and catalogues, associated with particular exhibitions (e.g., Arnold Newman, Irving Browning, Government by Choice, Childe Hassam Flag Paintings, Jasper Cropsey, Jackie Robinson, Pageant of Heraldry); Hudson River Book project; and various design proposals for the store itself (e.g., banners, brochures, catalog).
  - Set 1. Mc -Sca, 1984-1992 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-59)
    Includes production of Audubon poster; N-YHS participation in holiday gift shops at Morgan Guaranty and the Municipal Art Society; N-YHS's participation with a booth at the "New York is Book Country" book fair; store purchases for a Paris 1889 exhibition shop; publication of Tales of the Phelps-Dodge Family; product design work by Stephen Saitas; arrangements with Sandak for Audubon and other Slide-Paks; postcard project with Eastern Press; orders for posters for various objects (e.g., Bulls and Bears in the Market) and exhibitions including Government by Choice and Audubon; royalty fees to N-YHS for poster sales; sales of remainders.
  - Set 1. Sch -W, 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-40)
    Includes book signing for Simon Schama's History and Imagination: The Storyteller and the Detective; invoices for tote bags; production costs for slide-paks from Sandak for various exhibitions; N-YHS's participation in the Holiday Gift Fairs for Port Authority employees and at the Snug Harbor Cultural Center; receipts of store montlhy sales; press release in regard to the alliance between the Hudson River Club and N-YHS to celebrate the opening of the Luman Reed Gallery; and Tiffany-related products.
  - Set 2. Adirondack Store (2 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Set 2. Administration, 1988-1992 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes schedules and procedures.
  - Set 2. Audubon/Princeton Audubon Ltd. (2 folders), 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - Set 2. Bulls & Bears Poster Printing, 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
  - Set 2. Catalog Production. Museum Store (3 folders), 1986-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Set 2. Catalog. Luman Reed Collection, 1989 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
  - Set 2. Columbian Iconography, 1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
    Includes sketches of design for exhibition-related sales space.
  - Set 2. Course of Empire Reproduction Rights, 1985, 1992 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
  - Set 2. Damages in Store, Undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
  - Set 2. Memorandums, 1987-1991 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - Set 2. Phelps-Dodge Family Book Orders, 1988 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
  - Set 2. Requests for Catalogs and Sales Orders (5 folders), 1986-1992 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Set 2. Requests and Orders from Japan [Asia], 1991 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 14)
  - Set 2. Temporary Closing Letters (2 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 15-16)
- Series II. Catalogs and Inventories, 1966-1993, 2001; 1.33 Linear feet
  The series is arranged roughly by document type, ranging from internally-focused materials, such as inventories, to public documents, such as publicity materials and catalogs.
  The series includes documents that illustrate the items offered for sale by the museum store, publicity about those items, and sales records. The series includes the periodic inventories taken of stock through the 1980s into 1991, advertising flyers and order forms, descriptions and photographs of items, and the first five catalogs issued by the store (circa 1985-1991). There is also one catalog from a later period (2001). The period of 1990-1991 is especially well-documented as the store closed temporarily in late 1991 and underwent an analysis of its product line and sales; accordingly, there are detailed inventory and sales records for the 1990-91 period.
  - Store Inventories (9 folders), 1982-1992 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-9)
  - Store Inventory (Oversize), 1989 June 30 (Box OS-1, Folder -)
    Includes the complete store inventory taken at June 30, 1989.
  - Daily Log of Purchases, 1991-1992 June (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1)
  - Store Sales Records, 1990-1993 February (Offsite-box 8, Folder 2)
  - Book Lists (3 folders), 1980s-1992 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 3-5)
  - Holiday Sale Prices, 1991? (Offsite-box 8, Folder 6)
  - Audubon Mailing (Princeton Audubon Prints), 1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 7)
  - Order Form with Item List, 1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 8)
  - General Publicity Materials, circa 1990? (Offsite-box 8, Folder 9)
  - Christmas Holiday Cards and Flyers (3 folders), 1980s (Offsite-box 8, Folder 10-12)
  - Jewelry Descriptions, Undated (Offsite-box 8, Folder 18)
  - Catalog Photographs (9 folders), 1987-1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-9)
    Includes primarily photographs used for the store catalogs spanning 1987-1991. Also includes one photograph of the interior of the store and photographs for a Luman Reed publication.
  - Catalogue of Books, Pamphlets, Prints, & Postcards for Sale by N-YHS, 1966-1970s (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Card Catalog, 1980s (Offsite-box 10, Folder 2)
  - Museum Store Catalogs, Numbers 1-5 (5 folders), circa 1985-1990 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 3-7)
  - Museum Store Catalog, 2001 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 8)
- Series III. Products, 1930s?-1995; 0.25 Linear feet
  The series includes a small number of products sold by N-YHS, mostly postcards and holiday cards. Most of these items date from the 1970s and later, but the series also holds three sets of images sold in the 1930s (which were likely those donated to school groups; see New-York Historical Society General Correspondence, Series V [NYHS-RG 2]) and a 1949 souvenir booklet.
  The series is arranged with the oldest items first, followed by those from the late twentieth century, roughly by type of item.
  - N-YHS Picture Series I-III, 1930s-1940s? (Offsite-box 10, Folder 9)
    Consists of three sets of images: "Old New York in Pictures," "Leaders in American Democracy," and "John Rogers and his Statuette Groups."
  - N-YHS Picture Series I, 1930s? (Offsite-box 10, Folder 10)
    Consists of fragile "Old New York in Pictures" materials.
  - N-YHS Picture Series II, 1930s? (Offsite-box 10, Folder 11)
    Consists of fragile "Leaders in American Democracy" materials.
  - N-YHS Souvenir Booklets, 1949 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 12)
    Consists of three N-YHS souvenir booklets made for mailing and printed by Richard Bennett Talcott.
  - Holiday Cards by N-YHS, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 13)
  - Postcards, undated (Offsite-box 10, Folder 14)
    Consists of several postcards printed by Arthur Jaffe Heliochrome Company.
  - Proofs for Product, 1949, 1985? (Offsite-box 10, Folder 15)
    Proofs include images reproduced by Cartier. It is unclear if these proofs were turned into product.
  - Antique Advertising Postcards, 1985 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 16)
    Consists of a booklet of 24 Ready-to-Mail Postcards from the Bella C. Landauer Collection, published by Dover Publications.
  - Rare Birds of China Postcards, 1995 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 17)
    Consists of two booklets of artist J. Fenwick Lansdowne's Rare Birds of China prints.
  - Declaration of Independence on Reproduced Parchment, 1977 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 18)
    Consists of three reproductions of the Declaration of Independence.
  - Moving In The City: Three Centuries of Transportation in New York Portfolio, Circa 1977 (Box OS-1, Folder -)
    Consists of four portfolios of posters, postcards, greeting cards, and other reproductions related to the Transportation exhibition. The contents of two of the four portfolios are enclosed and complete. One portfolio is enclosed and complete except for its contents list. The fourth portfolio is open, with missing content.